Finlay mss., 1953-1972 LMC 1406
Lilly Library
Finlay mss.
1953-1972
Lilly Library
Finlay, Ian Hamilton.
LMC 1406
4011 Items 6 boxes, 3 oversize
The Finlay mss., 1953-1972, consists of the correspondence and writings of Ian Hamilton Finlay, 1925-2006, poet of Stonypath, Dunsyre, Lanarkshire, Scotland, where he published works from The Wild Hawthorn Press and of material sent to Finlay for inclusion into issues of Poor. Old. Tired. Horse.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
The Finlay mss., 1953-1972 contains of correspondence and writings by Ian Hamilton Finlay (1925-2006). An influential proponent of concrete poetry, Finlay moved from solely literary forms of poetry, drama, and short stories in the 1950's to kinetic forms of poetry expressed in stone, wood, neon and other tangible structures in the 1960's. Boats and boating, sails and the sea were used by Finlay to suggest poetic ideas in many of his poems such as Archangel of Archangel, Boatyard, Four Sails, The Four Seasons..., Homage to Gomringer, Little Drummer boy, The Old Nobby, Seashells, Sepia Barge and others. Sundials were used in like manner as in Arcadian Sundials, Biggar Sundial, and Land/Sea Indoor Sundial. Letters exchanged with woodcarvers, stone carvers, photographers, typographers, printers, and artists give the instructions for the creation of many of his works. A book of poems, Poems to See and Hear, was prepared especially to introduce to children Finlay's poetic concepts. During 1968 to 1971 there was much work by Films of Scotland in the preparation of the films Ocean Stripe 5 and KY 365 based on Finlay's life and poetry.
Following an agreement with the Fulcrum Press in June 1968 to publish an edition of The Dancers Inherit the Party, a controversy developed over the next several years concerning the first appearance of the work. This involved lengthy correspondence with solicitors, members of parliament, librarians, staffs of magazines, newspapers, arts councils, and literary organizations as well as close friends and poets.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings; III. Drawings and Photographs; IV. Printed.
Scope and Content Note
The Finlay mss., 1953-1972, consists of the correspondence and writings of Ian Hamilton Finlay, 1925-, poet of Stonypath, Dunsyre, Lanarkshire, Scotland, where he published works from The Wild Hawthorn Press and of material sent to Finlay for inclusion into issues of Poor. Old. Tired. Horse. Writings by Ian Hamilton Finlay include both his literary efforts and instructions for his creative works as well as photographs of some of them.
Other items in the collection include drawings by Robert Frame, Roland Kempes, Zeljko D. Kunjundzic, John Picking, and Margo Sandeman; photographs of Finlay, his boat, and garden; and printed pieces by Finlay, by other writers, and of a miscellaneous nature.
Completing the collection are materials for POTH (Poor. Old. Tired. Horse.), a poetry periodical edited by Ian Hamilton Finlay for several years which provided an opportunity for collaboration by artist and poet. These include poems, proofs, and layouts, but not complete in every instance, for issues no. 7, 9, 12, 13, 15, 16, 17, 18, 20, 23 and 25. Projected issues by Jerome Rothenberg and Victor de Vasarely are designated as POTH Miscellaneous 1 and 2.
Note on Indexing Term - "Art": Also included are drawings of a garden setting for a Finlay poem.
Note on Indexing Term - "English Poetry": Letters are exchanged with other poets, artists, architects, designers in glass and photographers, all in pursuit of the construction of his poetry in concrete form.
Related Material
Finlay mss. II; also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Acquisition Information
Acquired 1973.
Concrete poetry; Art; English Poetry; Finlay, Ian Hamilton.; Finlay, Ian Hamilton. Dancers inherit the party.; Morgan, Edwin, 1920-; Siegel, Eli, 1902-1978; Solt, Mary Ellen.; Turnbull, Gael.; Valoch, Jirí.; Williams, Jonathan, 1929-2008; British Broadcasting Corporation.
- I. Correspondence (Box 1)
  Arrangement
  Preceded by one folder of biographical material. General correspondence is arranged chronologically, followed by an undated letter and Christmas cards.
  Scope and Contents
  Among the correspondents are:
  Robin Acland
  Wolfgang Ainberger
  George Albon
  James Allan
  Maxwell Allan
  Roberrto Altmann
  Diane Amussen
  David Angus
  Alain Arias-Misson
  G.Aroul
  Arthur Hunt & Hunt, solicitors
  Dana Atchley
  Martha Baird
  Janet D. Bane
  Stephen Bann
  Mary Elizabeth Barber
  Douglas Barbour
  Harry Jefferson Barnes
  Harry Barrett
  William Beattie
  Heinz Rudolf Beck
  Donald Bell
  Asa Benveniste
  John Betjeman
  Arthur Bickerton
  Charles Joseph Biederman
  Max Bill
  A.N. Blackwood
  Margaret Blyth
  Alan Bold
  Jerry Bowles
  Edward Brandabur
  Lesley Bratton
  Christian J. Braun
  Udo Breger
  Jürgen Brenner
  Tom Bridge
  Coburn Britton
  British Broadcasting Corporation
  G.F. Brown
  George Mackay Brown
  Ernst Brücher
  William Buchanan
  Basil Bunting
  Vincent Butler
  David A. Button
  John Mackenzie Calder
  Lyn Calwell
  Augusto de Campos
  Alistair Cant
  Christopher Carrell
  Patrick Caulfield
  Douglas Chambers
  Julia L. Cherne
  Susan Chernow
  Shiomi Chieko
  JoAnne Chittick
  Ulf Christensen
  Elizabeth T. Clark
  Thomas A. Clark
  Alan Clodd
  Henry Clyne
  Bob Cobbing
  Harold Cohen
  Mary C. Cohen
  Barry Cole
  William Rossa Cole
  Sir Edmund Gerald Compton
  Margaret Conn
  John Stewart Conn
  Seamus Cooney
  Michael Cormack
  Sidney Corman
  Ron Costley
  John Cotton
  Tom Leadbetter Cottrell
  Kenelm Cox
  Margaret Cox
  Robert Creeley
  J. Elisabeth Crommelin
  Arthur Charles William Crook
  Robin Crozier
  Helen Burness Cruickshank
  Edward W. Curtis
  Simon Cutts
  Audrey Daly
  Tam Dalyell
  Jose Antonio Da Silva
  Guy Davenport
  Hervé Delagrave
  Richard Demarco
  Stephen W. Dennis
  Stanislaw Drózdz
  Kenneth Duffy
  Alexander Arbuthnot Dunbar
  Robert Edward Duncan
  Douglas Eadie
  David McAdam Eccles, 1st viscount Eccles
  Jim Ede
  Larry Eigner
  Richard England
  Theodore Enslin
  Amelia Etlinger
  Susan Finlay
  William Ian Robertson Finlay
  Roy Fisher
  Maurice Fleming
  James Allan Ford
  Renate Froehlich
  Robin Fulton
  John Furnival
  Robert E. Galen
  Heinz Gappmayr
  Ian Gardner
  John Gardner
  George Garson
  Rod Gathercole
  K.C. Gay
  Tony Gill
  Elizabeth L. Glazebrook
  Duncan Munro Glen
  Hamish Glen
  Sydney McK. Glen
  Sue Glover
  David Godwin
  Mathias Goeritz
  Eugen Gomringer
  Stephen Goode
  Arnold Abraham Goodman, baron Goodman
  Goodman Derrick & Co., solicitors
  Giles Alexander Esme Gordon
  Nigel Gosling
  Jennifer Gough-Cooper
  R.C. Gowers
  Peter Grant
  Douglas Gray
  Mrs. Ann (Giffard) Greenhill
  Basil Jack Greenhill
  Christopher Murray Grieve
  Murray Grigor
  Ronald Gunn
  Daniel J. Haberman
  Hagart & Burn-Murdoch, W.S., solicitors
  George Alexander Eugene Douglas Haig, 2nd earl Haig
  Barry L. Hall
  Douglas Hall Myles
  D.G. Hardie
  H. Forsyth Hardy
  P.R. Harris
  Judith Constance Mary (Ridehalgh) Hart
  Michael Harvey
  Oliver Hawkins
  Vaughn Hay
  Michael Heller
  Hamish Henderson
  James Findlay Hendry
  J. N. Herbert
  John Herdman
  Richard C. Higgins
  Hugh Creighton Hill
  Mark Hill
  Mary Cranford (Coates) Hitchens
  Sydney Ivon Hitchens
  Philip Welsby Holland
  Stephen Holland
  Sally Holman
  Michael Horovitz
  Pierre Sylvester Houédard
  Libby Houston
  W.J. Hummerstone
  Gordon Huntley
  H.C. Huntley
  T. & W. Ide
  A.C. Ijenberg
  Charles d'Orville Pilkington Jackson
  Ruth L. Jacoby
  Ernest Jandl
  John MacLane Johansen
  Ronald Johnson
  Bernard Karpel
  Graham Keen
  Robert Kelly
  Robert C. Kennedy
  X.J. Kennedy
  Hugh Kenner
  Irena Kenod
  Alexander Kerr
  Nick Kimberley
  David Kindersley
  M.J. King
  Melanie Kingdon
  Dorothy Koppelman
  Richard Kostelanetz
  Ferdinand Kriwet
  Zeljko D. Kujundzic
  John Lambert
  Brian Lambie
  Barry Lane
  Phyllis Larkin
  James Laughlin
  George L. Lawson
  Robert Lax
  Jennie Lee
  David Leigh
  Theodore Ferdinand Lentz
  D.A. Levy
  Jill Liddington
  Nicholas Logsdail
  Else B. Lorch
  R.L.C. Lorimer
  Andrew Lothian
  John W. Lucas
  Edward Lucie-Smith
  Jack Lunam-Cowan
  A. McBean
  Patrick McCormack
  Thomas McGrath
  David Roy MacGregor
  Eric B. Mackay
  J.A. Mackenzie
  Michael S. Mackenzie
  Alastair Mackintosh
  Hamish McLaren
  J.N. McLaurin
  Ruari McLean
  John MacQueen
  David Jackson McWilliams
  Marvin Herbert Malone
  Anthony Richards Manser
  Edgar James March
  Linda Dorothy (Bowman) March
  Helen Marley
  Fred R. Martin
  John Kenneth Martin
  John Edward Matthias
  Charles Matz
  Ronald Mavor
  Hansjörg Mayer
  Roger Russell Maylone
  Freiderike Mayröcker
  G. Ropen Mead
  William Moelwyn Merchant
  Christopher Middleton
  Amado Ramón Millán
  Stuart Mills
  Deidre B. Montgomery
  Stuart Montgomery
  A. Doyle Moore
  Edwin Morgan
  Pete Morgan
  Alfred Morris
  James Munro
  Edward Nairn
  Julia Newman
  H. Alleyne Nicholson
  James Nicholson
  D.H. Nielsen
  Seiichi Niikuni
  Gunter Nolte
  Robert Nye
  Philip Oakes
  George A. Oliver
  Betty O'Looney
  Miles D. Orvell
  Charles Osborne
  Alicia (Suskin) Ostriker
  Derek Parker
  James Edmund Neil Paterson
  George Paterson
  John Pauker
  Noël Strange Paul
  Octavio Paz
  David Peace
  M.A. Pegg
  Paul N. Perrot
  Edward Phelps
  Anthony Phillips
  Omar Shakespear Pound
  Ian Douglas Ben Procter
  John Whitely Purser
  Michael Pye
  Geoffrey Rans
  David Raphael
  Walter M. Reid
  Robert Reiss
  Alan Riddell
  Ann Ridley
  Bridget Riley
  Francis Warren Roberts
  John Roberts
  Lewis Findlay Robertson
  Duncan Robinson
  Pamela Robinson
  William T. Rodgers
  Herbert M. Rosenthal
  Macha Louis Rosenthal
  Ian G. Ross
  Ian Simpson Ross
  Bertram Rota
  Jerome Rothenberg
  Trevor Royle
  Rubinstein
  Nash & Co., solicitors
  Regina Ryan
  John Ryder
  Christopher Rye
  Magda Salvesen
  Margot Sandeman
  Oscar Sandner
  Aram Saroyan
  Robert Crombie Saunders
  Estella Schmid
  John Scholfield
  Stephen Scobie
  James Robert Seaton
  A.J. Seely
  Annabel Seidler
  Martin Seymour-Smith
  Arnold Shaw
  Jessie (McGuffie) Sheeler
  Michael R. Shepherd
  Elizabeth Shub
  Eli Siegel
  Stanley M. Simpson
  James Simson
  Leif Sjoberg
  Joan Skalley
  Philip Sked
  Alisdair Skinner
  Christopher Small
  Barbara (Brodo) Herrnstein Smith
  John L. Smith
  Hans Sohm
  Mary Ellen (Bottom) Solt
  Kaim Spalte
  John Hanbury Angus Sparrow
  Charles Spencer
  Juliet Standing
  Derek Stanford
  Margaret (Holdsworth) Stanford
  Philip Steadman
  Jeffrey Steele
  Jeremy V. Steele
  Mary Stevens
  F.R. Stevenson
  Donald James Stewart
  Peter Stitt
  Constance Stungo
  Andrew Suknaski
  Geoffrey Summerfield
  John T. Sutherland
  Michael F. Sydenham
  Robert Tait
  Diane Tamnes
  Eric Taylor
  Eyvind S. Tew
  John R. Thorpe
  Ian Tinwell
  Karl Torok
  John Hugh Tuohy
  Gael Turnbull
  Charles Turner
  Enrique Uribe Valdivielso
  Jirí Valoch
  Franz Vanderlinden
  Victor de Vasarely
  David Vaughan
  Paul de Vree
  Herman de Vries
  Frank W. Weatherhead
  Mike Weaver
  Peter Weibel
  Steve Whealton
  Charlene H. White
  Eric Walter White
  John William Mills Willett
  Ann (Stevenson) Williams
  Emmett Williams
  Jonathan Chamberlain Williams
  Angus Frank Johnstone Wilson
  Astrid Wilson
  Gloria Wilson
  Trevor Winkfield
  Melinda Winters
  Joyce Wittenborn
  Woodford & Ackroyd, solicitors
  Howard Woolmer
  Edward Wright
  Kit Wright
  Pedro Xisto
  Alan Young
  Bill Zavatsky
  Nicholas Zurbrugg
  Consult the Manuscripts Index in the Library for dates of letters of individual correspondents.
  - Biographical, 1962 - 1968, Nov. (Box 1)
  - 1968, Dec. - 1969 (Box 2)
  - 1970, Jan. - Dec. 21 (Box 3)
  - 1970, Dec. 22 - 1972, Jan. (Box 4)
  - letters; Christmas cards, 1972, Feb. - Dec.; undated (Box 5)
  - letter, May 30, 1967; June 4, 1969; undated (Oversize 1)
- II. Writings (Box 5)
  Arranged alphabetically by title of Finlay's work, followed by writings by others, arranged alphabetically by author.
  Includes writings, drawings and related materials. Writings by Ian Hamilton Finlay.
  - Writings by Finlay (Box 5)
    - ABCD... (Box 5)
    - Acrobats (Box 5)
    - Additional poems (Box 5)
    - Ajar (Box 5)
    - Alphabet book (Box 5)
    - and/between/in (Box 5)
    - april may june july... (Box 5)
    - Arcadian Sundials (Box 5)
    - The Archangel (Box 5)
    - ark-arc (Box 5)
    - Au Pair (Box 5)
    - Blok (Box 5)
    - A boatyard (Box 5)
    - Bring Back the Birch (Box 5)
    - Broken Heart (Box 5)
    - Brother of the Dogfish (Box 5)
    - Caterpillar in Pond (Box 5)
    - Christmas was at Easter (Box 5)
    - Ceolfrith Street Handout (Box 5)
    - Count-down of a fir tree (Box 5)
    - Cythera: Garden Setting (Box 5)
    - The Dancers Inherit the Party (Box 5)
    - Earthship (Box 5)
    - The Estate Hunters (Box 5)
    - Evening/Sail 2 (Box 5)
    - Fir Tree (Box 5)
    - Fishing News News (Box 5)
    - flags (Box 5)
    - The flower of the fal (Box 5)
    - The Four Seasons as Fishing Boats (Box 5)
    - From "An Inland Garde (Box 5)
    - Headlines (Box 5)
    - Hic Jacet parvulum… (Box 5)
    - Homage to Donald McGill (Box 5)
    - Homage to Vuillard (Box 5)
    - Homage to A. E. Hornel (Box 5)
    - Horizon (Box 5)
    - Instructions about boat to Salamander Press (Box 5)
    - Instructions for setting poems (Box 5)
    - It is little (Box 5)
    - Joke book (Box 5)
    - Land/Sea Indoor Sundial (Box 5)
    - The Land's Shadow (Box 5)
    - A memory of summer (Box 5)
    - A minor Incident (Box 5)
    - The mouse (Box 5)
    - Nets (Box 5)
    - Notes about the Fulcrum Press Affair (Box 5)
    - Notes, miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - The Old Nobby (Box 5)
    - The Olsen Excerpts (Box 5)
    - Original Verses (Box 5)
    - Pan Loaf Provincialism (Box 5)
    - Peasants (Box 5)
    - Picture Book (Box 5)
    - Pittodrie (Box 5)
    - Poem with Three Stripes (Box 5)
    - Poems (Box 5)
    - Postcard poem Layouts (Box 5)
    - A Rock Rose (Box 5)
    - The Rubenstein Questionnaire (Box 5)
    - A Sailor's Calendar (Box 5)
    - Sails/Waves (Box 5)
    - Sea poppy 1. (Box 5)
    - Sea-poppy 2. (Box 5)
    - A Sea Street Anthology (Box 5)
    - Seas/ease (Box 5)
    - The Sea's Waves... (Box 5)
    - Sepia Barge (Box 5)
    - The Sign of the Nudge (Box 5)
    - Skylarks (Box 5)
    - Stack Net (Box 5)
    - Tree-Shells (Box 5)
    - Tristan's Sail (Box 5)
    - Two Concrete poems (Box 5)
    - Unicorn (Box 5)
    - Walking through Seaweed (Box 5)
    - Wave Sheaf (Box 5)
    - The Wild Dogs in Winter (Box 5)
    - Willing Wings (Box 5)
    - Windflower (Box 5)
    - Xmas morn (Box 5)
    - you me us (Box 5)
    - The Little Drummer Boy (Oversize 1)
    - Seashells (Oversize 1)
    - Tye, Cringle, etc. (Oversize 1)
    - Be in Time... (Oversize 3)
    - The Bigger Sundial (Oversize 3)
    - Column Poem (Oversize 3)
    - Evening Will Come (Oversize 3)
    - Four Sails (Oversize 3)
    - The Four Seasons as Fore-and-Afters (Oversize 3)
    - Glossary (Oversize 3)
    - Homage to Gomringer (Oversize 3)
    - Love/Apple (Oversize 3)
    - Poems to Hear and See (Oversize 3)
    - A Rococo Walnut (Oversize 3)
    - Sailing Barge (Redwing) (Oversize 3)
  - Writings by others (Box 6)
    - Albert-Birot, Pierre (Box 6)
    - Bann, Stephen (Box 6)
    - Braga, Edgard (Box 6)
    - Brown, Pete (Box 6)
    - Campos, Augusto de (Box 6)
    - Cant, Jackie (Box 6)
    - Careme, Maurice (Box 6)
    - Chopin, Henri (Box 6)
    - Clark, Elizabeth T. (Box 6)
    - Costley, Ron (Box 6)
    - Cox, Kenelm (Box 6)
    - Creeley, Robert (Box 6)
    - cummings, e.e. (Box 6)
    - Cutts, Simon (Box 6)
    - Demarco Gallery (Box 6)
    - Dragomirescu, Radu (Box 6)
    - Falk, Gunter (Box 6)
    - Gappmayr, Heinz (Box 6)
    - Gomringer, Evgen (Box 6)
    - Grigor, Murray (Box 6)
    - Hendry, James Finlay (Box 6)
    - Higgins, Richard C. (Box 6)
    - Hill, Hugh Creighton (Box 6)
    - Hollo, Anselm (Box 6)
    - Horovitz, Michael (Box 6)
    - Houston, Libby (Box 6)
    - Johnson, Ronald (Box 6)
    - Jandl, Ernst (Box 6)
    - Kujundzic, Zeljko D. (Box 6)
    - Lax, Robert (Box 6)
    - McCaig, Norman (Box 6)
    - McDowell, John D. (Box 6)
    - McGerrill, Ann (Box 6)
    - Malone, Marvin Herbert (Box 6)
    - Mayrocker, Friederike (Box 6)
    - Melo Castro, E.M (Box 6)
    - Mills, Stuart (Box 6)
    - Morgan, Edwin (Box 6)
    - Niikuni, Seiichi (Box 6)
    - Novak, Ladislov (Box 6)
    - Riddel, Alan (Box 6)
    - Roth, Karl Heinz (Box 6)
    - Scha, Remko J.H (Box 6)
    - Seidman, Hugh (Box 6)
    - Siegel, Eli (Box 6)
    - Simmons, Robert (Box 6)
    - Smith, Barbara (Bodo) Hirrnstein (Box 6)
    - Sparrow, John Hanburg Angus (Box 6)
    - Standford, Derek (Box 6)
    - Sutherland, Robert Garioch (Box 6)
    - Supervielle, Jules (Box 6)
    - Turnbull, Gael (Box 6)
    - Uribe Valdivie Iso, Enrique (Box 6)
    - Valoch, Jiri (Box 6)
    - Vree, Paul de (Box 6)
    - Wild Hawthorn Press (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Williams, Jonathan Chamberlain (Box 6)
    - Zukofsky, Louis (Box 6)
    - Unknown authors (Box 6)
    - Scobie, Stephen (Oversize 1)
- III. Drawings & Photographs (Box 6)
  - Drawings (Box 6)
    - Fraine, Robert (Box 6)
    - Kempes, Roland (Box 6)
    - Kujundzic, Z.D., (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Picking, J. (Box 6)
    - Sandeman, Margot, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - McNeish, Alexander (Oversize 1)
  - Photographs (Box 6)
    - ASA Exhibition in Tokyo (Box 6)
    - Brazilian Concrete Poets: Augusto and Haroldo de Campos, and Dècio Pignatari (Box 6)
    - Cruz-Diez, Carlos. Artwork (Box 6)
    - Finlay, I.H. Concrete poems, garden, pond and boat, two portraits (Box 6)
    - Gomez de Liano, Ignacio. Poetry (Box 6)
    - Niedecler, Lorine. Snapshot (Box 6)
    - Schmalriede, Manfred, photographer. Finlay exhibit (Box 6)
    - Schiller, Robert M., photographer. Louis Zukofsky (Box 6)
    - Trace, M.D., photographer. Artwork by Jeffrey Steele (Box 6)
    - Walker, Audrey, photographer. For Finlay's Autumn poem (Box 6)
- IV. Printed (Box 6)
  - The Archangel of Archangel (Box 6)
  - A Boatyard (Box 6)
  - Catches (Box 6)
  - Cythera (Box 6)
  - Fishing News News (Box 6)
  - Homage to E.A. Hornel (Box 6)
  - A memory of Summer (Box 6)
  - The Old Nobby (Box 6)
  - Pole Night (Box 6)
  - Seashells (Box 6)
  - Tree-Shells (Box 6)
  - Willing Wings (Box 6)
  - Other writers (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous 1 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous 2 (Box 6)
  - P.O.T.H. (Poor. Old. Tired. Horse). (Oversize 2)
    Includes poems, proofs, and layouts